

Email: <a href="mailto:consultant@londonresearchinternational.com">consultant@londonresearchinternational.com</a> www.LondonResearchInternational.com

# Mr A. Katekar

**NATIONALITY**: Indian

#### **SUMMARY**

Confident and Creative Quality Assurance & Quality Control Engineering Professional with 19 years of distinguished performance in Quality Assurance & Quality Control fields. Exceptional work ethics and commitment to organizational objectives within the fast changing marketplace. Multi-disciplined versatility with superb trouble-shooting and analytical skills to assess problems and provide expert on-site reliable solutions. Recognized for proven ability to face challenges head-on with a Team Leadership qualities.

#### **EXCELLENT KNOWLEDGE OF CODES & STANDARDS**

- ASME (American Society of Mechanical Engineers)
- TEMA (Tubular Exchanger Manufacturers Association)
- AWS (American Welding Society)
- API (American Petroleum Institute)
- BS (British Standards)
- European Norms (EN Standards)
- Vast experience of working in ISO 9001 environment ASME Coded vessels manufacturing and quality control.

#### **EDUCATION**

Diploma in Mechanical Engineering-AMIE-Part-I

#### PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATIONS

ASNT Certified NDT Level II in RT, UT, MT & PT
Appearing ASNT Level III Exam in Nov 2013 in RT & PT
Appeared API Exam in June 2013 in API 510

## **EMPLOYMENT RECORD**



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com

www.LondonResearchInternational.com

### 1) Dec 2009 to till Date

Position: Freelancer for,

- Blue & Green Consultants Pvt. Ltd.
- UHDE INDIA PVT LTD for Mumbai, Pune & Vadodara
- DET NORSKE VERITAS AS for Pune and Mumbai
- Lindinger inspection, US & India
- Prime 4 Inspection Dubai UAE
- Indian Inspection Services Pune & Mumbai

I am working in the capacity Project Quality Engineer for Domestic Project such as IOCL, BPCL, Reliance, NOCL, & some the LSTK projects such as Praxair, DCW, and Jayshree Chemicals, GACL for Chemical / Petrochemical. Also few of the overseas Client such as Gulf Farabi, Gulf Flour, Siemens-Australia, QA Management. Velosi Australia, Punj Lloyds, Simon Carves, Dealim Korea, DSME, Enerflex, PDO, PT Tripatra Indonesia, Technico, etc.

## **RESPONSIBILITIES (PQM)**

- Liaise with the Client, subcontractors, as agreed upon with the Project Manager, as far as quality-related matters are concerned
- Verify, comment and approve Quality documents of subcontractors
- Develop an internal audits plan as well as an audits plan on project subcontractors and sub suppliers
- Implement corrective actions and follow their close-out by co-operating with the Project Manager and the Project Engineering Manager in solving contractual nonconformities as well as concessions and deviations requests related to QC.
- Coordinate, Expediting & witness the Quality Control activities
- Manage Project Quality Control activities, report about his activities to the Project
   Manager and require production interruption when quality-affecting problems arise.
- Verify that inspections defined in the ITP are actually carried out during the different phases of job execution
- Coordinate supervision activities at the yard, materials certification and goods precommissioning
- Witness of the NDE and final tests carried out by contractor and/or external personnel
- Coordinate all activities necessary for final tests



Email: <a href="mailto:consultant@londonresearchinternational.com">consultant@londonresearchinternational.com</a> www.LondonResearchInternational.com

- Stage wise, in process & Final inspection of Pressure Vessels, Heat Exchangers, Large Storage Tanks, Roof Tanks, Internal Floating Roof Tanks, and Cone Roof Tanks Boilers and Pipeline, Valves, Pumps.FRP & Rubber lining.
- Auditing fabrication at sub-contractors
- Review of various NDT reports
- Documentation and inspection of Power Boilers, Gas Turbines, Steam Turbines, Diesel
   Fuel Oil Storage Tanks, Steel Structures etc.
- Site Inspection of various construction activities such as witnessing the welder qualification, alignment of various static and rotating equipments, welds setups etc.
- Quality Assurance and Quality Control of the construction activities and
- compliance to the Contract Specifications.
- Packing control & Pre shipment inspection witness

#### Witnessing of various NDT and onsite inspection of all the following:

- Gas turbine and auxiliaries.
- Back pressure steam turbines and auxiliaries.
- Waste heat recovery boilers and auxiliaries.
- Plant closed cooling water system.
- Diesel Fuel Oil Storage Tanks and transmission pipelines.
- Instrument and Service air system.
- Heating Ventilation and Air Conditioning system.
- Complete Fire protection system.
- Diesel generators and compressors.
- Boiler feed water treatment.
- Closed Cooling Water system & Lube Oil cooling System & VAM Chiller Package

#### 2) Oct 1994 to Nov 2009

Employer: Ion Exchange (I) Ltd. Mumbai India

Designation: Deputy Manager Quality Control (International Division)

#### Responsibilities:

A) Mechanical:



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com

www.LondonResearchInternational.com

- Manage the welding program through PQR, WPS, Welder test, weld inspections. Assist failures, suggest repairs, & insures that all repairs, modification, alternations are meeting the company standards.
- Inspection of Boilers and pressure vessels, Boilers tubes, heat exchangers, pipe lines, compressors etc. By Standard codes
- Maintain equipment history.
- Work hand to hand with assessment team,
- Co-Ordination with QA/QC Activities.
- Review of WPS /PQR.
- Witness of welder qualification as per the ASME Sec IX.
- Daily weld audit inspection according to the relevant WPS records.
- The Quality of work intact, thereby to minimize the rework percentage.
- Inspection of welding consumables complying with the approved welding procedures and maintain the baking records of Low Hydrogen Electrodes.
- Inspection of bevel preparation, joint fit-up, and weld visual inspection.
- Witnessing pre-heating and post- weld heat treatment as per the specification requirement & as well as verification of heat treatment chart.
- Carry out welding inspection in site, with approved packages by verifying the materials
  as per spec, choosing the right welding technique, performing the inspection required
  and furnishing reports.
- Hardness test for weld and HAZ.
- Interpretation of Radiographic films as per the API-1104, ASME 31.1, and ASME31.3 & ASME Section VIII.
- Carry out hydro test of pipe, exchangers and vessels.
- Dimensional Inspection of flange, Fitting and prefabrication spools check chemical Analysis with respect to heat No. with MTC and Visual inspection as per there TMS (Tec knowledge methods and standards).
- PMI verification (positive material identification).
- Visual inspection for expansion bellows joint as per data sheet.
- Conducting all NDT tests like UT, RT, MPT, and PT&VT for their different units like EU/EG/PP/UTL/PE.
- Carry out all NDT testing including ultrasonic testing for RBI jobs (Risk based
- Inspection).
- Trained and worked with the ultrasonic creeping wave method with IRIS NDT of



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com

 $\underline{www.LondonResearchInternational.com}$ 

- Ethylene glycol reactor scanning. (To find stress cracks)
- Wire ropes inspection:
- The following tests were witnessed as per IS2266-2000 at Usha Martin in 2007 for Chennai
- Petrochemical Company Ltd.and Adani power SEZ Mundra Gujarat under FITCHNER.
- Construction
- Factor of Safety
- Nominal breaking load,
- Safe working load
- Tensile designation of wire
- Type of core/Lay direction
- Length of Rope/Material Grade
- Visual inspection:
- Absence of defects i e Damages, twist, opening of the wires, No corrosions
- Diameter of the ropes
- Wire Finish
- Manufacturing identifications.

# B) Electrical, Instrumentation & rotating Equipments:

# Valves:

- Carry out inspection for all types of valves i e Manual/Auto, Motorized for Butterfly, Diaphragm, Ball, NRV etc in line with ITP & Approved specs.
- Stage wise inspection witness of Butterfly/Diaphragm, valves for Hydro, poring/foundry witness.NDT i e Radiography P Test for special MOC in line with ITP if required Pre-shipment inspection of valves to ensure Qty, Size, Labeling and Sipping Mark control also, witness for visual check for absence of defects, imperfections, deformations, corrosions etc.
- Documents review (MTC, INTERNAL TEST REPORTS, Q-RECORDS, PART LIST, and SPECTION

#### **Pumps / Agitators**

 Carry out inspection of performance test, hydro, impeller balancing dimensional check etc



Email: <a href="mailto:consultant@londonresearchinternational.com">consultant@londonresearchinternational.com</a> www.LondonResearchInternational.com

• Stage wise inspection witness of High Pressure pumps for Hydro, poring/foundry witness in line with ITP if required.

- Pre-shipment inspection of pumps to ensure Qty, Labeling and Sipping Mark control also, witness for visual check for absence of defects, imperfections, deformations, corrosions etc.
- Documents review (MTC, INTERNAL TEST REPORTS, Q-RECORDS, PART LIST, and SPECTION & STANDARDS etc.

#### Instrumentation:

- Carry out inspection for Level switches, Level Indicators, Flow Transmitters, and Rotameters, in line with Appd ITP.
- Pre-shipment inspection of valves to ensure Qty, Size, Labeling and Sipping Mark control also, witness for visual check for absence of defects, imperfections, deformations, corrosions etc.
- Documents review (MTC, INTERNAL TEST REPORTS,Q-RECORDS,PART LIST,SPECTION & STANDARDS etc.)

#### 3) April 1991 to Nov 1993

Employer: M/s Techno Consultant Mumbai

Designation: Field Engineer

## Responsibilities:

- Practical hands on in the quality related activities of a variety of Pressure vessels,
   Storage Tanks, SS,MS and FRP Piping, Ruberlining equipments, Structural, Field erected storage tanks, etc.
- Construction projects including plant piping, pipe lines and storage tanks, Valves,
   Pumps, Instruments etc. in compliance with national and International standards of codes. Welding and Non Destructive Testing, in service inspection.
- Engaged in Quality Assurance activities like ITP preparation and coordination with Quality control department for effectiveness, training the personnel and analyzing the data for improving the efficiency and quality having a successful track record in:
- Water and Waste water Treatment
- Steel and Power sector
- Pharmaceuticals



 $\label{lemail:consultant@londonresearch international.com} \\ \underline{ www.LondonResearch International.com} \\ \\ \underline{ www.LondonResearch International.com} \\ \\ \\ \\ \underline{ www.LondonResearch International.com} \\ \\ \underline{ www.LondonResearch International.com} \\ \\ \underline{ www.LondonResearch International.com} \\ \underline{ www.LondonResearch International.$ 

- Pulp and paper
- As per the National and International code standard.

#### **PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS**

Associate Member of American Society for Non-destructive Testing (ASNT)

Member of American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME) is under Registration

Associate Member of API.